This is Aunt Zip from Sodom, North Carolina.
هذه " آنت زيب " من " سودوم " شمال كاليفورنيا
She was 105 years old when I took this picture.
وقد كان عمرها 105 سنوات عندما إلتقطت لها هذه الصورة
She was always saying things that made me stop and think, like,
وكانت تقول أشياءً تجعلني أتوقف وأفكر قليلاً .. مثل
"Time may be a great healer, but it ain't no beauty specialist."
" الزمن مداوٍ رائع للجروح ولكنه ليس خبير تجميل "
(Laughter)
( ضحك )
She said, "Be good to your friends.
وكانت تقول " عليك أن تعامل أصدقائك بصورة جيدة "
Why, without them, you'd be a total stranger."
لماذا .. لانك بدونهم سوف تكون مجرد غريب
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
This is one of her songs.
وهذه واحدة من أغانيها
Let's see if we can get into the flow here and all do this one together.
لنرى إن كان بإمكاننا أن نغني معاً ونندمج مع الإيقاع
And I'm going to have Michael Manring play bass with me.
وسوف يقوم " ميشيل مانرين " بعزف الإيقاع معي
Give him a big old hand.
صفقوا له تصفيقاً حاراً
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
One, two, three, four.
1 , 2 , 3 , 4
(Music)
(موسيقى )
Well, my true love's a black-eyed daisy;
حسناً .. حبيبتي ذات العيون السوداء " ديزي "
if I don't see her, I go crazy.
إن لم أراها .. أُجن
My true love lives up the river;
حبي الحقيقي يعيش هنالك عند النهر
a few more jumps and I'll be with her.
بضع قفزات وسأكون هنالك معها
Hey, hey, black-eyed Susie! Hey, hey, black-eyed Susie!
هيه هيه .. ديزي ذات العيون السوداء , هيه هيه ...ديزي ذات العيون السوداء
Hey, hey black-eyed Susie, hey.
هيه هيه ديزي ذات العيون السوداء هيه
Now you've got to picture Aunt Zip at 105 years old in Sodom, North Carolina.
الآن عليكم أن تتخيلو " انت زيب " في 105 من عمرها في سودوم في شمال كاليفورنيا
I'd go up and learn these old songs from her.
وكنت أستيقظ وأذهب إليها لكي أتعلم الأغاني القديمة منها
She couldn't sing much, couldn't play anymore.
ولم تكن تستطيع الغناء جيدا .. ولم تعد تستطيع العزف
And I'd pull her out on the front porch.
وكنت اسحبها إلى المنصة الأمامية للمنزل
Down below, there was her grandson plowing the tobacco field with a mule.
وكان أمامنا حفيدها يحرث حقل من التبغ بواسطة بغل
A double outhouse over here on the side.
وكانت مساحة فناء كبيرة في ذلك الجانب
And we'd sing this old song. She didn't have a whole lot of energy,
وكنا نغي هذه الأغنية القديمة .. ولم تكن تقوى على غنائها بأكملها
so I'd sing, "Hey, hey!" and she'd just answer back with, "Black-eyed Susie."
وكنت أٌول " هيه هيه " وهي تقول .. " ديزي ذات العيون السوداء "
Oh, hey, hey, black-eyed Susie! Hey, hey, black-eyed Susie!
آووه هيه . هيه ديزي ذات العيون السوداء .. هيه هيه ... ديزي ذات العيون السوداء
Hey, hey, black-eyed Susie, hey.
هيه هيه .. ديزي ذات العيون السوداء هيه
Well, she and I went blackberry picking.
حسناً .. وكنا أحيانا نذهب لقطف التوت البري
She got mad; I took a licking.
وكانت تغضب عندما كنت أتذوق البعض
Ducks on the millpond, geese in the ocean,
البط في ميلبوند .. والأوز في المحيطات .
Devil in the pretty girl when she takes a notion.
والشر في طفلة جميلة عندما يخطر على بالها فكرة
Hey, hey, black-eyed Susie! Hey, hey, black-eyed Susie!
هيه هيه .. ديزي ذات العيون السوداء .. هيه هيه ديزي ذات العيون السوداء
Hey, hey black-eyed Susie, hey.
هيه ديزي ذات العيون السوداء هيه
Let's have the banjo.
لنعزف قليلاً بواسطة آلة البنجو
Well, we'll get married next Thanksgiving.
حسناً .. سوف نتزوج في عيد الشكر القادم
I'll lay around; she'll make a living.
سوف أستلقي وستقوم هي بإعالة المنزل
She'll cook blackjacks, I'll cook gravy;
سوف تطبخ هي " العوامات " وسوف أطبق أنا " المرق "
we'll have chicken someday, maybe.
وقد نطبخُ يوماً الدجاج .. ربما
Hey, hey, hey, hey. Hey, hey, black-eyed Susie, hey!
هيه هيه هيه هيه هيه هيه ديزي ذات العيون السوداء هيه
One more time now.
مرة أخرى
Oh, hey, hey, black-eyed Susie! Hey, hey, black-eyed Susie!
آووه هيه هيه ديزي ذات العيون السوداء هيه هيه ديزي ذات العيون السوداء
Hey, hey, black-eyed Susie, hey.
هيه هيه ديزي ذات العيون السوداء هيه
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Thank you, Michael.
شكراً مايكل
This is Ralph Stanley.
هذا رالف ستانلي
When I was going to college at University of California
عندما كنت ذاهباً إلى جامعة كاليفورنيا
at Santa Barbara in the College of Creative Studies,
في سانت باربرا .. في كلية الدراسة الإبداعية
taking majors in biology and art, he came to the campus.
لأحصل على تخصص في البيولوجيا والفن .. جاء هو إلى الحرم الجامعي
This was in 1968, I guess it was.
كان هذا في عام 1968 .. هكذا أعتقد
And he played his bluegrass style of music,
وقد كان يعزف هو موسيقى من نوع البلو
but near the end of the concert, he played the old timing style of banjo picking
ولكن في نهاية الحفل .. كان يعزف نوعا قديماً من البانجو
that came from Africa, along with the banjo.
هذا النوع جاء من أفريقيا .. مع البانجو
It's called claw-hammer style, that he had learned from his mother and grandmother.
ويدعي " مخلب المطرقة " وقد كان تعلمها من والدته .. وجدته
I fell in love with that.
وقد أغرمت بهذا على الفور
I went up to him and said, how can I learn that?
وذهبت إليه وقلت له .. كيف يمكنني أن أتعلم هذا ؟
He said, well, you can go back to Clinch Mountain, where I'm from,
فقال لي .. حسناً يمكنك أن تعود إلى جبل كلينش .. حيث مسقط رأسي
or Asheville or Mount Airy, North Carolina --
أو اشيفيل او مونت أيري .. شمال كاليفورنيا ..
some place that has a lot of music.
فهي أماكن مازالت تنبض بالموسيقى
Because there's a lot of old people still living that play that old style.
بسبب أن كبار السن هنالك مازالوا يعزفون ذلك النمط من الموسيقى
So I went back that very summer.
وقد ذهب هنالك في الصيف التالي ..
I just fell in love with the culture and the people.
وقد أغرمت بالثقافة والأشخاص هناك
And you know, I came back to school, I finished my degrees
ومن ثم - كما تعلمون - عدت إلى الجامعة وأكملت تعليمي
and told my parents I wanted to be a banjo player.
وأخبرت والدي أنني أريد أن أغدو عازف بانجو
You can imagine how excited they were.
ويمكنكم تخيل مدى حماستهم جراء ذلك ..
So I thought I would just like to show you some of the pictures
لذا فكرت .. أن اريكم بعض الصور
I've taken of some of my mentors.
التي إلتقطتها لمرشديَّ الموسيقين
Just a few of them, but maybe you'll get just a little hint of some of these folks.
بعضهم فحسب .. ولكن ربما سوف تميزون بعض هؤلاء الأشخاص
And play a little banjo. Let's do a little medley.
وسوف أعزف القليل من البانجو .. لنقم بهذه المعزوفة
(Music)
(موسيقى)
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Those last few pictures were of Ray Hicks, who just passed away last year.
هذه الصور الأخيرة هي ل " راي هيكز " والذي توفي السنة الماضية
He was one of the great American folk tale-tellers.
وقد كان واحدا من أفضل قاصي القصص الأمريكين
The Old Jack tales that he had learned -- he talked like this,
وقد كانت قصة " جاك " القديمة والتي كان يتحدث بها .. وكان يتحدث على هذه الشاكلة
you could hardly understand him. But it was really wonderful.
وكان من الصعب جداً إستيعابه .. ولكنه كان رائعاً فعلاً
And he lived in that house that his great-grandfather had built.
وقد عاش في هذا البيت .. وهو الذي بناه جده الأكبر سابقاً
No running water, no electricity. A wonderful, wonderful guy.
بدون امددات مياه .. أو كهرباء .. رائع .. رجل رائع
And you can look at more pictures.
ويمكنكم مشاهدة المزيد من الصور.
I've actually got a website that's got a bunch of photos that I've done
في الواقع لدي موقع إلكتروني فيه مجموعة من هذه الصور التي إلتقطت
of some of the other folks I didn't get a chance to show you.
بعضها لبعض الأشخاص الذين لا أملك فرصة لكي أعرض صورهم لكم .
This instrument came up in those pictures. It's called the mouth bow.
هذه الآلة الموجودة في الصورة تدعى "الفم القوس " - ماوس بو -
It is definitely the first stringed instrument ever in the world,
إنها حتما الآلة الوترية الأولى في العالم
and still played in the Southern mountains.
ومازالت تستخدم في الجبال الجنوبية
Now, the old timers didn't take a fancy guitar string and make anything like this.
الآن .. الموزعون الموسيقيون القدامى لم يكن لديهم هذا الجيتار الوتري الخيالي ليقوموا بهذا ..
They would just take a stick and a catgut and string it up.
فقد كانوا يحضرون عصى ويربطون إليها وتراً
It was hard on the cats, but it made a great little instrument.
وقد كان الأمر صعباً .. ولكنها كانت آلة رائعة
It sounds something like this.
وكان صوتها كما هذا ..
(Music)
(موسيقى)
Well, have you heard the many stories told by young and old with joy
حسناً .. هل إستمعتم قديما إلى عدة قصص قديمة مروية بروح الشباب والمتعة
about the many deeds of daring that were done by the Johnson boys?
عن عدة أمور مليئة بالتحدي والجرأة قام بها فتية جونسون ؟
You take Kate, I'll take Sal; we'll both have a Johnson gal.
خذوا أنتم شخصية " كيت " وأنا سأخذ سام .. وسوف نكون سوية " جونسون جال "
Now, they were scouts in the rebels' army,
الآن .. لقد كان هنالك كشافة في جيش المتمردين
they were known both far and wide.
وقد كانوا معروفين على نطاق واسع
When the Yankees saw them coming, they'd lay down their guns and hide.
لدرجة أن اليانكيز عندما شاهدوهم قادمون .. أنزلوا مسدساتهم وإختبأوا
You take Kate, I'll take Sal; we'll both have a Johnson gal.
خذوا أنتم شخصية " كيت " وأنا سأخذ سام .. وسوف نكون سوية " جونسون جال "
Ain't that a sound?
اليس هذا صوتاً رائعاً
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Well, it was 1954, I guess it was.
حسناً .. لقد كنا في عام 1954 .. هكذا أعتقد
We were driving in the car outside of Gatesville, Texas,
وكنا نقود السيارة خارج مدينة " جيتسفيل " في تكساس
where I grew up in the early part of my life.
حيث نشأت في بداية حياتي
Outside of Gatesville we were coming back from the grocery store.
خارج " جيتسفيل " كنا عائدون من متجر خضراوات
My mom was driving; my brother and I were in the back seat.
وكانت والدتي تقود السيارة .. وكنت أجلس مع أخي في مؤخرتها
We were really mad at my mom. We looked out the window.
وكنا غاضبين جداً من والدتي .. وكنا ننظر من النافذة
We were surrounded by thousands of acres of cotton fields.
وكنا محاطون بآلاف الهكتارات من حقول القطن
You see, we'd just been to the grocery store,
أترون .. لقد خرجنا على التو من متجر الخضار
and my mom refused to buy us the jar of Ovaltine
وقد رفضت والدتي شراء مرطبان فالتين لنا ..
that had the coupon for the Captain Midnight decoder ring in it.
والذي كان يحوي على كوبون لكابتن منتصف الليل ومزين بخاتم عليه
And, buddy, that made us mad.
ولقد جعلنا نغضب حقاً
Well, my mom didn't put up with much either, and she was driving, and she said,
حسناً .. ولكن والدتي لم تُطق هذا .. وقالت وهي تقود ..
"You boys! You think you can have anything you want.
" أتنظنون يا أطفال أنه يمكنكم أن تحصلوا على أي شيء تريدونه ؟ "
You don't know how hard it is to earn money. Your dad works so hard.
" ألا تعلمون كم هو صعب الحصول على النقود .. إن والدكم يعمل جاهد ليؤمنه لكم "
You think money grows on trees. You've never worked a day in your lives.
" هل تظنون أن النقود تنمو على الشجر
You boys make me so mad. You're going to get a job this summer."
لقد جعلتموني أغضب فعلاُ .. سوف تعملون في هذا الصيف
She pulled the car over; she said, "Get out of the car."
ومن ثم أوقفت السيارة وقالت " إخرجوا من السيارة الآن "
My brother and I stepped out of the car.
وخرجنا أنا وأخي من السيارة
We were standing on the edge of thousands of acres of cotton.
وكنا نقف على حافة حقول القطن تلك
There were about a hundred black folks out there picking.
وكان هنالك مئات من الرجال السود يقطفون القطن
My mom grabbed us by the shoulders. She marched us out in the field.
ومن ثم أمسكت والدتي بنا من أكتافنا .. وسيرتنا داخل الحقل
She went up to the foreman; she said,
وذهبت إلى الرجل المسؤول عنهم وقالت ..
"I've got these two little boys never worked a day in their lives."
" لديَّ هذين الطفلين وهما لم يعملا يوما في حياتهم
Of course, we were just eight and 10.
حتماً .. فقد كانت أعمارنا 8 و 10 سنوات
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
She said, "Would you put them to work?"
وقالت " لماذا لا تضعهما في أحد الأعمال لديك "
Well, that must have seemed like a funny idea to that foreman:
حسناً .. وقد بدت فكرة مضحكة لذلك الرجل في تلك اللحظة
put these two middle-class little white boys out in a cotton field
أي أن تضع طفلين من الطبقة المتوسطة في حقول القطن
in August in Texas -- it's hot.
وفي شهر أغسطس في تكساس .. وهو شهرُ حار
So he gave us each a cotton sack,
وقد أعطت كل منا كيساً للقطن
about 10 feet long, about that big around, and we started picking.
وهو عبارة عن كيس طوله 10 أقدام ..إنه بهذا الكبر .. وقد بدأنا بالقطف
Now, cotton is soft but the outside of the plant is just full of stickers.
الآن القطن يبدو ناعماً ولكنه من الخارج  مليء بالأشواك
And if you don't know what you're doing,
وإن لم تكن خبيراً بما تقوم به
your hands are bleeding in no time.
فإن يديك سوف تمتلىء بالدماء بوهلة
And my brother and I started to pick it,
وقد بدأنا أنا وأخي نقطف القطن
and our hands were startin' to bleed, and then -- "Mom!"
وقد بدأت يدانا تنزف الدماء ,, " أمي "
And Mom was just sitting by the car like this.
وكانت والدتي تجلس في السيارة
She wasn't going to give up.
ولم تكن على وشك أن تعدل عن رأيها
Well, the foreman could see he was in over his head, I guess.
حسناً .. وقد كان القائم على العمل هائما في فكره .. على ما أظن
He kind of just snuck up behind us and he sang out in a low voice.
وكان يسير خلفنا .. ويغني بصوت خافت
He just sang: "Well, there's a long white robe in heaven, I know.
وكان يغني " حسناً .. هنالك حبل عريض طويل في الجنة .. أعرفه "
Don't want it to leave me behind.
لا يريد أن يتركني لوحدي
Well, there's a long white robe in heaven, I know.
حسناً .. هنالك حبل عريض طويل في الجنة .. أعرفه
And from all around as people started singing and answering back, he sang:
وبدأ الجميع حوله يغنون ويدندنون خلفه .. وكان يغني
"Good news, good news: Chariot's coming.
أخبار جيدة , أخبار جيدة : شاريوت قادم
Good news: Chariot's coming.
أخبار جيدة : شاريوت قادم
And I don't want it to leave me behind."
ولا أريد أن أترك أحداً خلفي "
Now, my brother and I had never heard anything like that
وقد لم نكن قد سمعنا شيئاً مثل هذا من ذي قبل - أنا وأخي -
in our whole lives. It was so beautiful.
طيلة حياتنا .. وقد كان غناءً رائعاً
We sat there all day picking cotton, without complaining,
وقد بقينا طيلة اليوم نقطف القطن بدون أي تذمر
without crying, while they sang things like:
بدون بكاء .. بينما كانوا يغنون هكذا ..
"Oh, Mary, don't you weep, don't you moan" and "Wade in the water,"
" آه يا مريم .. لا تنتحبي .. لا تتألمي .. وإسبحي في الماء "
and "I done done," "This little light of mine."
فقد قمت بما قمت .. وهنالك ضوء صغير في نفسي
Finally, by the end of the day,
وفي نهاية اليوم ..
we'd each picked about a quarter of a bag of cotton.
كنا قد ملئنا ربع كيس من القطن
But the foreman was kind enough to give us each a check for a dollar,
وقد كان المسؤل عن العمل كريما وأعطانا شيكاُ بقيمة دولار
but my mother would never let us cash it.
ولكن والدتنا لم تسمح لنا بصرفه
I'm 57; still have the check.
وانا اليوم أبلغ من العمر 57 سنة ومازلت أحتفظ بذلك الشيك
Now, my mother hoped that we learned from that the value of hard work.
وقد أملت والدتي أن نتعلم قيمة العمل وصعوبته من ذلك الموقف
But if you have children, you know it doesn't often work that way.
ولكن إن كان لديك أطفال فأنت تعرف ان الأمور لن تسير هكذا
No, we learned something else.
فقد تعلمنا شيئاً آخر
The first thing I learned that day
وأول شيء تعلمته ذلك اليوم
was that I never ever wanted to work that hard again.
هو أنني لن أعمل مرة أخرى نهائيا
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And pretty much never did.
وفعلاً تقريباً لم أعمل مرة أخرى
But I also learned that some people in this world
وتعلمت أيضاً أن هنالك بعض الاشخاص في العالم
do have to work that hard every day, and that was an eye-opener.
يتوجب عليهم العمل كل يوم عملاً مرهقاً وقد وسع ذلك أفقي كثيراً
And I also learned that a great song can make hard work go a little easier.
وقد تعلمت أيضاً أنه بأغنية واحدة رائعة يمكن أن تُذلل صعاب العمل بسهولة
And it also can bring the group together in a way that nothing else can.
ويمكنها ايضاً أن توحد مجموعة من الناس بصورة لا يمكن لأي شيء أخر أن يقوم بها
Now, I was just a little eight-year-old boy that day
لقد كنت إبن ثمان سنوات في ذلك اليوم
when my mama put me out of the car in that hot Texas cotton field.
الذي وضعتني فيه والدتي في حقل القطن ذاك في تكساس تحت الشمس الحارقة
I wasn't even aware of music -- not even aware of it.
ولم أكن أعي يومها وجود الموسيقى - لم أكن أعي وجودها
But that day in the cotton field out there picking,
ولكن في ذلك الوقت في حقل القطن الذي كنا نحصد منه
when those people started singing,
عندما بدأ هؤلاء الأشخاص بالغناء
I realized I was in the very heart of real music,
أدركت من صميم قلبي أن الموسيقى
and that's where I've wanted to be ever since.
هي الشيء الذي خلقت من أجله
Try this old song with me. I sing:
حاولوا أن تغنوا هذه الأغنية معي . أنا أغني :
Well, there's a long white robe in heaven, I know.
حسناً .. هنالك حبل عريض طويل في الجنة .. أعرفه
You sing: Don't want it to leave me behind.
وأنتم تغنون : لا يريد أن يتركني لوحدي
Don't want it to leave me behind.
لا يريد أن يتركني لوحدي
Good news, good news: Chariot's coming.
أخبار جيدة : شاريوت قادم
And I don't want it to leave me --
ولا أريده أن يتركني
It's been a while since you guys have been picking your last bale of cotton, isn't it?
لقد مضى وقت طويل مذ كنا نقطف القطن هناك أليس كذلك؟
Let's try it one more time.
لنحاول مرة أخرى
There's a starry crown in heaven, I know.
هنالك تاج مرص بالنجوم في السماء أعلمه
Don't want it to leave me behind.
لا يريد أن يتركني لوحدي
Good news: Chariot's coming.
أخبار جيدة : شاريوت قادم
It was a few years ago, but I sort of remembered this story,
لقد كانت هذه القصة منذ عدة سنوات ولكني مازلت أتذكرها
and I told it at a concert.
وقد قلت هذه القصة في حفل سابق
My mom was in the audience.
كانت والدتي تحضره
After the -- she was glad to have a story about herself, of course,
وبعد -- لقد كانت فخورة بأن تُحكى قصة عنها بالطبع
but after the concert she came up and she said,
وبعد الحفل جاءت إلي لتقول
"David, I've got to tell you something.
دايفيد , لديّ شيءٌ أخبرك به
I set that whole thing up.
لقد رتبت كل هذا مسبقاً
I set it up with the foreman. I set it up with the owner of the land.
فقد إتفقت مع مسؤل العمل في الحقل ومع صاحب الأرض
I just wanted you boys to learn the value of hard work.
بأن يعلمكما درساً عن قيمة العمل
I didn't know it was going to make you fall in love with music though."
ولم أكن أعتقد أن هذا سيجعلك تقع في غرام الموسيقى
Let's try. Good news: Chariot's coming.
هيا لنحاول : أخبار جيدة : شاريوت قادم
Good news: Chariot's coming.
أخبار جيدة : شاريوت قادم
And I don't want it to leave me behind.
لا يريد أن يتركني لوحدي
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Well, this is the steel guitar. It's an American-made instrument.
حسناً .. هذا جيتار معدني .. وهو صناعة أمريكية
It was originally made by the Dopyera Brothers,
وقد صنع في الأساس بواسطة " الاخوين دوبيرا "
who later on made the Dobro, which is a wood-bodied instrument
والذي صنع لاحقا ال "دوبرو " وه آلة موسيقية جسدها مصنوع من الخشب
with a metal cone for -- where the sound comes from.
مع مخروط معدني .. وهو الذي يخرج منه الصوت
It's usually played flat on your lap.
وهي تعزف عادة وهي موضوعةٌ على حجرك
It was made to play Hawaiian music back in the 1920s,
وقد صنعت في الاساس لعزف الموسيقى لأهل هاواي في عام 1920
before they had electric guitars, trying to make a loud guitar.
قبل أن يصنعوا الجيتار الكهربائي ..محاولين صناعة جيتار ذا صوت مرتفع
And then African-American folks figured out you could take a broken bottle neck,
ومن ثم قام الرفاق الافروأميركان باستخدام عنق زجاجة مكسورة
just like that -- a nice Merlot works very well.
تماما كهذا -- وعنق زجاجة مارلوت جيدة جدا
That wine we had yesterday would have been perfect.
فتلك العبوة التي تحوي النبيذ التي تناولته البارحة ستكون ممتازة للامر
Break it off, put it on your finger, and slide into the notes.
اكسرها .. ضعها على اصبعك ومن ثم اعزف النغمات
This instrument pretty much saved my life.
هذه الالة أنقذت حياتي
Fifteen years ago, 14 years ago, I guess, this year,
منذ 15 أو 14 عاما .. كما أعتقد
my wife and I lost our daughter, Sarah Jane, in a car accident,
لقد فقدنا إبنتنا .. ساره جين في حادث سيارة
and it was the most -- it almost took me out -- it almost took me out of this world.
ولقد كان هذا الامر الأفظع والذي كاد تقريباً أن يدفعني إلى الانتحار
And I think I learned a lot about what happiness was
وقد تعلمت ماذا تعني السعادة جراءه
by going through such unbelievable grief,
عن طريق المضي قدما في هذا الحزن البليغ
just standing on the edge of that abyss and just wanting to jump in.
فلطالما وقفت على حافة الجرف وكنت أنوي القفز
I had to make lists of reasons to stay alive.
ومن قم كتبت قائمة لماذا يجب أن أبقى على قيد الحياة
I had to sit down and make lists, because I was ready to go;
وجلست لكتابتها وكنت على وشك الانتحار
I was ready to check out of this world.
كنت على وشك التخلي عن هذا العالم
And you know, at the top of the list, of course,
أتعلمون .. كان على قمة القائمة
were Jenny, and my son, Zeb, my parents -- I didn't want to hurt them.
جيني .. وإبني زيب .. ووالدي .. فلم أكن أريد أن أؤذيهم
But then, when I thought about it beyond that,
ومن ثم تجاوزت الامر
it was very simple things.
وقد كان الامر شديد البساطة
I didn't care about -- I had a radio show,
فقد كنت لا أعبأ -- كنت أملك برنامجا إذاعيا
I have a radio show on public radio, "Riverwalk,"
برنامجا إذاعيا على راديو محلي " ريفير ولك "
I didn't care about that. I didn't care about awards or money or anything.
ولم أكن أعبأ بهذا .. لم أكن أعبأ بالجوائز ولا بالنقود ولا بأي شيء
Nothing. Nothing.
لا شيء .. لا شيء
On the list it would be stuff like,
ومن الأشياء التي كانت على القائمة
seeing the daffodils bloom in the spring, the smell of new-mown hay,
رؤية تفتح أزهار النرجس في الربيع .. وإستنشاق رائحة القش المقصوص حديثاً
catching a wave and bodysurfing, the touch of a baby's hand,
الركب على موجة .. ولمسة الطفل الصغير
the sound of Doc Watson playing the guitar,
وصوت "دوك واطسون " وهو يعزف على الجيتار
listening to old records of Muddy Waters and Uncle Dave Macon.
والاستماع إلى الأغاني القديمة ل " مادي ويترز " و العم " ديف ماكون "
And for me, the sound of a steel guitar,
وبالنسبة لي ..صوت الجيتار المعدني .
because one of my parents' neighbors just gave me one of these things.
لان أحد جيران والدي كان قد أهداني إحداها
And I would sit around with it, and I didn't know how to play it,
وكنت أجلس بالقرب منه ولا أعرف كيف أعزف عليه
but I would just play stuff as sad as I could play.
ولكنني كنت أعزف وبأكثر طريقة حزينة يمكنكم تخيلها
And it was the only instrument that, of all the ones that I play,
وقد كانت الآلة الوحيدة من بين كل الآلات التي أعزف عليها
that would really make that connection.
التي صنعت معها هذه الرابطة
This is a song that came out of that.
وكانت هذه الأغنية التي أعزفها
(Music)
(موسيقى)
Well, I hear you're having trouble.
حسنا , لقد سمعت أنك واقع في المشاكل
Lord, I hate to hear that news.
إلهي كم أكره أن اسمع هذه الاخبار
If you want to talk about it, you know, I will listen to you through.
إذا أردت أن تتحدث عن الامر فانني كما تعلم سوف أستمع إليك
Words no longer say it; let me tell you what I always do.
لا يوجد كلمات أُخرى يمكن قولها .. لأخبرك ماذا أقوم به عادة
I just break off another bottleneck and play these steel guitar blues.
أنا أكسر عنق قنينة ومن ثم أعزف البلوز على الجيتار المعدني
People say, "Oh, snap out of it!"
يقول الناس " آووه , إخرج من هذه الحالة ! "
Oh yeah, that's easier said than done.
وهو سهل القول صعب الفعل
While you can hardly move, they're running around having all kinds of fun.
فبينما يكاد يكون الحراك مستحيلاً .. يكونون يجرون ويدورن حولك ملئين بالفرح
Sometimes I think it's better just to sink way down in your funky mood
وأحيانا أفكر .. آه لو أغرق في مزاجك الغريب هذا
'til you can rise up humming these steel guitar blues.
حتى أستطيع أن أخرج من حالتي مهمهما بموسيقى البلوز على هذا الجيتار المعدني
Now, you can try to keep it all inside
والآن يمكنك أن تترك كل هذا بداخلك
with drink and drugs and cigarettes,
وأن تحستي الكحول والمخدرات والسجائر
but you know that's not going to get you where you want to get.
ولكنك تعلم جيداً أن هذا لن يوصلك إلى المكان الذي تريد ان تصل اليه
But I got some medicine here that just might shake things loose.
ولكني أستخدمت بعض الادوية في تلك الفترة لكي أُنقذ نفسي من بعض الاشياء التي كانت تحدث لي
Call me in the morning after a dose of these steel guitar blues.
إتصل بي في الصباح بعد جرعة من البلوز بواسطة الجيتار المعدني وسترى
Open up now.
والان إبتهج
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Oh, I think I've got time to tell you about this. My dad was an inventor.
آه .. أعتقد انني املك الوقت لكي اخبركم بهذه القصة .. لقد كان والدي مخترعا
We moved to California when Sputnik went up, in 1957.
وقد انتقلنا الى كاليفورنيا عام 1957 عندما انطلق سبوتنيك الى الفضاء
And he was working on gyroscopes;
وقد كان يعمل على الجيروسكوبات
he has a number of patents for that kind of thing.
وقد كان قد حصل على عدة براءات اختراع لهذه الامور
And we moved across the street from Michael and John Whitney.
وكنا قد انتقلنا الى منزل يقع على بعد شارع من منزل " ميشيل وجون ويتني "
They were about my age.
وكانا بمثل عمري
John went on, and Michael did too,
وقد كبر جون وميشيل ليصبحا
to become some of the inventors of computer animation.
لاحقا من المبتكرين للرسوم المتحركة على الكمبيوتر
Michael's dad was working on something called the computer.
وقد كان والد ميشيل يعمل على الكمبيوتر في تلك الاثناء
This was 1957, I was a little 10-year-old kid;
وقد كان هذا في عام 1957 .. وكنت إبن 10 سنوات حينها
I didn't know what that was. But he took me down to see one,
ولم اكن اعلم ما هذا .. ولكنه أخذني لكي أراه
you know, what they were making. It was like a library,
والذي كانو يقومون به حينها ... لقد كان كما المكتبة
just full of vacuum tubes as far as you could see,
مليئ بأنابيت تشبه أنابيب المكنسة ومتكدسة بالكم الكبير الذي يمكن تخيله
just floors and floors of these things,
وطبقات وطبقات منها
and one of the engineers said,
وقد قال احد المهندسين
some day you're going to be able to put this thing in your pocket.
يوما ما سوف تضع كل هذا الشيء في جيبك
I thought, damn, those are going to be some big pants!
وقلت في نفسي اللعنة سيتوجب علي شراء بنطال بجيوب اكبر
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So that Christmas -- maybe I've got time for this --
لذا في عيد رأس السنة - ربما املك وقتا لكي اقص هذا -
that Christmas I got the Mister Wizard Fun-o-Rama chemistry set.
في ذلك العيد قمت بعمل منصة " ميستير ويذرد فن او روما " للمواد الكيميائية
Well, I wanted to be an inventor just like my dad; so did Michael.
كنت أريد ان اكون مخترعا كما كان والدي وكذلك ميشيل
His great-granddad had been Eli Whitney,
وقد كان جده الكبير هو " ايلي وين "
the inventor of the cotton gin.
الذي اكتشف جين القطن
So we looked in that --
وقد نظرنا الى هذا ..
this was a commercial chemistry set.
وقد كانت منصة مواد كيميائية تباع
It had three chemicals we were really surprised to see:
وكان فيها 3 مواد كيميائية مدهشة
sulfur, potassium nitrate and charcoal.
الكبريت ونترات البوتاسيوم والفحم
Man, we were only 10, but we knew that made gunpowder.
وقد كنا ابناء 10 اعوام وكنا قد قررنا ان نصنع بارود البندقيات
We made up a little batch and we put it on the driveway
وقد صنعنا قليلا منه ووضعناه في الممر
and we threw a match and phew, it flared up. Ah, it was great.
ومن ثم قمنا برمي شعلة عليه وقد اشتعل وقد كان ذلك رائعا
Well, obviously the next thing to do was build a cannon.
ومن ثم كان الهدف التالي هو بناء مدفع
So we went over into Michael's garage --
فذهبنا الى كراج ميشيل
his dad had all kinds of stuff, and we put a pipe in the vice there,
فقد كان يوجد فيها كل شيء .. ووضعنا في انبوب بارز كان موجودا
and screwed a cap on the end of the pipe,
ومن ثم ربطنا احد اطرافه
drilled a hole in the back of the pipe, took some of our firecrackers,
وحفرنا حفرة في هذا الانبوب .. واخذنا بعضا من الالعاب النارية
pulled out the fuses, tied them together, put them in the back there,
وسحبنا منها الفتيل وربطناها معا ومن ثم عدنا الى الخلف
and -- down in that hole -- and then stuffed some of our gunpowder
ومن ثم عبئنا الانبوب بالبارود صرخنا - قنبلة في الحفرة -
down that pipe and put three ball bearings on the top, in the garage.
صحيح وضعنا في داخل الانبوب ثلاث كرات معدينة كان في الكراج حينها
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
We weren't stupid: we put up a sheet of plywood about five feet in front of it.
ولم نكن حمقى فقد وضعنا لوحا من الخشب على بعد خمسة اقدام من الانبوب
We stood back, we lit that thing,
ورجعنا الى الوراء ,, وتركنا الامور تاخذ مجراها
and they flew out of there -- they went through that plywood like it was paper.
وقد اخترقت الكرات الثلاث .. اللوح الخشبي كما لو انه ورقة
Through the garage.
واخترقت الكراج
Two of them landed in the side door of his new Citroen.
وقد اصابت اثنتين منهم باب سيارة ستروين جديدة
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
We tore everything down and buried it in his backyard.
ودمرنا كل شيء على الفور ودفنا الادوات في الساحة الخلفية
That was Pacific Palisades; it probably is still there, back there.
وكان هذا في منطقة " الباليساديس باسفيك " وهي على الاغلب مازالت هناك
Well, my brother heard that we had made gunpowder.
حسناً , سمع أخي اننا صنعنا بارود قنابل ..
He and his buddies, they were older, and they were pretty mean.
وقد كان هو ورفاقه أكبر منا عمرا وقد كانو اشد لؤماً
They said they were going to beat us up
وقالوا لنا أنهم سيشبعونا ضرباً
if we didn't make some gunpowder for them.
اذ لم نصنع لهم بارود قنابل
We said, well, what are you going to do with it?
وسئلناهم بماذا سوف تستخدمونه
They said, we're going to melt it down and make rocket fuel.
قالوا انهم سوف يذيبونه وسوف يصنعون وقود صواريخ
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Sure. We'll make you a big batch.
وبالطبع .. صنعنا كمية كبيرة منه
So we made them a big batch, and it was in my --
اذا .. صنعنا كمية كبيرة منه .. وقد كانت في --
now, we'd just moved here. We'd just moved to California.
كنا قد إنتقلنا للتو إلى كاليفورنيا
Mom had redone the kitchen; Mom was gone that day. We had a pie tin.
وكانت والدتي قد جددت المطبخ وكانت خارج المنزل يومها بعد أن أعدت لنا فطيرة التونا
It became Chris Berquist's job to do the melting down.
وقد كانت مهمة كريس بيرجيست أن يذيب البارود
Michael and I were standing way at the side of the kitchen.
وكنا نقف انا وميشيل على جانب المطبخ
He said, "Yeah, hey, it's melting. Yeah, the sulfur's melting.
وقال " ياااه .. هيه .. إنه يذوب .. الكبريت يذوب "
No problem. Yeah, you know."
لا مشكلة .. كما تعلمون
It just flared up, and he turned around, and he looked like this.
فقد اشتعل فقط وإلتفت إلينا وقد كان يبدو هكذا
No hair, no eyelashes, no nothing.
بدون شعر .. بدون رموش ,, بدون أي شيء
There were big welts all over my mom's kitchen cabinet;
وقد إمتلأ مطبخ والدتي بالكدمات
the air was the just full of black smoke.
وكان الهواء مشبعا بالدخان الاسود
She came home, she took that chemistry set away, and we never saw it again.
وعندما عادت الى المنزل اخذت منصة الكيمياء تلك ولم نراها مذ ذلك الوقت
But we thought of it often, because every time she'd cook tuna surprise
وكنا نتذكرها في كل مرة كانت تطبخ التونا لنا
it made -- tasted faintly of gunpowder.
ونشعر أن مذاقها مثل البارود
So I like to invent things too,
لذا فانا احب ان اخترع أيضاً
and I think I'll close out my set with something I invented a good while back.
وسوف أُنهي بواسطة شيء إخترعته منذ مدة
When drum machines were new, I got to thinking,
عندما كانت الطبول جديدة .. فكرت
why couldn't you take the oldest form of music, the hambone rhythms,
لماذا لا يمكننا الاستفادة من اقدم اشكال الموسيقى , " ايقاعات " هامبون "
and combine it with the newest technology?
ودمجها مع التكنولوجيا الجديدة
I call this Thunderwear.
انا ادعو هذا " ثندر وير "
At that time, drum triggers were new.
وقد كان في ذلك الوقت مشغلات الطبول جديدة
And so I put them all together and sewed 12 of them in this suit.
لذا وضعتهم معا ومن ثم ربطت 12 واحدة منهم في هذه البدلة
I showed you some of the hambone rhythms yesterday;
وقد اريتكم البارحة بعضا من " ايقاعات هامبون "
I'm going to be doing some of the same ones.
وسوف اقوم بالمثل الآن
I have a trigger here, trigger here, here, here. Right there.
لدي مشغل هنا و هنا وهنا ... ومشغل هنا
It's going to really hurt if I don't take that off. Okay.
وسوف تؤلمني حقاً إن لم أخلعها ..
Now, the drum triggers go out my tail here, into the drum machine,
والآن تستمر هذه المشغلات الى الاسفل من وراء ظهري وحتى الطبل
and they can make various sounds, like drums.
ويمكنها ان تخرج عدة اصوات مختلفة " اصوات طبل "
So let me put them all together. And also, I can change the sounds
حسنا دعوني اضعهم معا .. وسوف أغير الاصوات
by stepping on this pedal right here, and --
بالسير على هذه الدواسة هنا
let me just close out here by doing you a little
دعوني أختم بهذه المقطوعة الصغيرة
hambone solo or something like this.
من " الهامبون " كهذه
Thank you, folks.
شُكراً يا أصحاب
(Applause)
(تصفيق)